PHILIP GREENSPUN: All right.
We're going to go in
and outline, how do you
navigate an airplane?
It's become a lot easier
now in the GPS age,
but you still have
to know a little bit
about how people used to
do it in the old days,
partly to pass the
exam, and partly
because it's interesting.
All right.
So we're going to talk about
looking out the window.
That's called pilotage,
planning your flight
and then looking out the window.
We'll talk about the old
non-directional beacons,
basically homing in
on a radio station.
In the 1950s, there was
something called the VOR
that we'll talk about
that lets you figure out
exactly your magnetic heading
to or from a radio station.
And finally, the
way that most people
get around these days, the
GPS and the moving map.
OK.
So when you're doing pilotage,
you come up in advance
with a bunch of visual
landmarks that you think you'll
be able to see from the air.
You're going to cross a river.
You're going to
find a reservoir.
You're going to see
a big radio tower.
You're going to
pass a town that has
the name of the town written in
a high school athletic field.
And the VFR charts,
they emphasize--
I think you saw that,
maybe with the iPad
or we have charts up here.
We can look at it later--
but they emphasize objects that
you can, as a practical matter,
see from the air.
So the procedure, and we'll
go through this carefully,
is you plot your planned course
using a pencil and a ruler,
essentially, on the chart.
You select what
checkpoints are going
to be visible on your flight.
You measure the distance
from point to point,
and then you've got
this plan of what
heading you're going to steer.
You get the forecast
winds as well.
So you say, look, I'm
going to fly this.
I'm going to be going 100
knots over the ground.
I'm going to be being blown
off course very slightly
by a crosswind from the north.
You plan all of that.
And then you've got your navlog.
So as you reach each checkpoint,
you can make a correction.
Well, it took me a little
bit longer to get here.
I'm a little bit left of
where I thought I was.
So you can make these
corrections as you go along.
All right.
So here's an example.
Let's say you wanted to go
from MIT to Bennington College
to visit a friend.
Well, there's an airport
right there called DDH,
and it's about 90
nautical miles.
I think I did this
with a SkyVector.
So your planning goal is to come
up with this navigation log.
So you're going to say, OK,
I'm going to depart Hanscom
Field up there at the top.
And it's going to take me--
looks like it's going to
take me nine nautical miles
before I reach my cruising
altitude and about
four minutes.
Then after that, it's going
to take me five minutes
to reach Fitchburg
Airport, which
airports are great landmarks.
They're very easy to see and
they have distinctive shapes.
And notice here, the
magnetic course is 298,
but with the wind,
we're going to have
to correct that and steer 292.
And of course, the compass
card with the deviations
indicated might give us
another degree or two.
But basically, from the
wind, that wind correction
is going to have us steering
a slightly different course.
Anyway, so you're going to come
up with this navlog of how long
it's going to take,
what course you're
going to steer from your
compass, and as you go along,
you're basically doing
what's called dead reckoning.
It's tough over the
ocean because there's not
any landmarks.
So those early pilots who went
over oceans were real heroes.
If you're going over the
land, you can actually
make these corrections.
So the procedure
is just as I said.
You plot the course
on the chart.
You measure the true course.
So let's say you're
going straight north.
That's going to be zero.
Then you correct
for the forecast
wind to find the true heading.
Then you correct for
the magnetic variation
because remember, you're
in-aircraft sources
are magnetic heading,
not true heading.
And finally, you're going
to estimate the ground speed
and estimated time
and route for a leg.
All right.
Let's talk about some terms.
We're using them,
let's reinforce them.
Your course is the
direction over the ground,
but your heading is
going to be, in general,
different from the
course due to wind.
True is if you steer true north,
you'll get to the North Pole
and hang out with Santa Claus.
If you go magnetic, you'll go
to a slightly different place
every time.
All right.
Magnetic variation, we had
this chart pretty much before.
So unless you're
somewhere down in Florida
or it looks like
in Chicago, there's
going to be some correction
from true to magnetic.
The local magnetic
variation, remember,
is indicated on the chart.
So it's right here,
14 degrees west,
and remember, again, if you
get confused about how true
and magnetic relate, just
look at the OR diagram.
Here's an example,
a compass card
that you might see
in your aircraft.
I haven't seen any that
are quite this dramatic.
I think this is for effect,
but you can see it says, look,
if you want to fly 60
degrees, a heading of 060--
oh, if you want to go east,
instead of steering 090,
steer 85 on your compass.
It gets updated every
couple of years, I think,
and as I added earlier,
if you have things
in the airplane or systems like
a heated windshield turned on,
the compass may become
kind of worthless.
All right.
So let's get out the tools.
We're going to go through these
more with flight planning.
But basically, you get
your sectional chart.
Tina showed you this.
I have one too.
I just got it yesterday at East
Coast Aero Club, front desk.
Flight schools
usually sell them.
I think they're missing
out on the revenue
now that it's all free on
SkyVector and similar sites.
You've got your plotter.
So this is basically
a ruler, and the ruler
is, on top, in statute miles.
I'm not sure when you would
ever want to use that,
but on the bottom, you
have nautical miles
which is what we generally
use in the aviation world.
And you have this
protractor that you
might remember from
elementary school that
helps you figure out,
on the chart, what
the true course is going to be.
All right.
So I think you guys can probably
figure out how to use that.
This is the E6B flight computer.
So I think the E6B designation
comes from the US military.
I'm not exactly sure
when this came out.
Probably it says in
Wikipedia, but I'm
assuming it was a World
War Ii era kind of device.
And it lets you make all kinds
of computations of density,
altitude, of how fast you're
going truly through the air,
as a function of your altitude
and what you're seeing
on your airspeed indicator.
It lets you, on the
backside, correct for wind.
You can make pencil
marks and then start
twisting to figure out whether
the wind is going to give you
a reduction or a
boost in airspeed,
and also how much of
a course correction
you're going to need.
So it's a very
useful instrument.
Now fortunately, it
comes with instructions
because your modern
pilots have mostly
forgotten how to use this.
It's a historical
artifact at this point.
But we'll go through some of it
so you'll get a flavor for it,
and it is fun.
All right.
So you put your plotter
down on the chart.
And as you can see,
you'll be able to read
from the protractor, depending
on the line that you've drawn,
what the course is.
I will tell you that one of
the most important skills,
if you're old-school
flight instructor,
is drawing a straight
line from one
side of the chart to the other.
I can't tell you how to do it.
It's a really complicated
folding system
that enables you to actually
draw a course line when
you have to flip the chart
over to get from your source
and destination airports.
OK.
Using the plotter, you
can see people's charts.
They would have to buy new ones
every few weeks because they
would be so marked
up with pencils.
Here we find the
true course is 038.
So as you can see,
they're just reading that
off the protractor part.
There are paper
E6Bs and metal ones.
So this is a picture
of a paper one.
Again, you can see
that you can just
set up, for example, that
we're going to go 90 knots,
and then that's here.
If we go 90 knots, then
it will take us 10 minutes
to go 15 miles.
Not very exciting.
The wind side is
more interesting.
You can get your ground speed
and your wind correction angle.
That's the most important thing.
So this one is hard enough
to use that they actually
put the instructions
right on the top here,
on the back of the E6B.
So they say, place the wind
direction under the true index.
We'll go through this.
Anyway, the wind's
from 210, and we're
trying to fly straight
south, a true course of 180
at an air speed of 147
knots through the air.
We've already computed that.
And the wind's 20
knots from 210.
So we're trying to go south.
Let's say, this is south
at 180 and the wind
is coming from the right.
So when we're all
done, I sure hope
that the answer
will be that we have
to steer a little bit to the
right of 180, true at least.
All right.
So here we are on the wind side.
We start by marking 147
knots, it looks like.
And then we rotate it.
You can see that pencil
mark has been rotated off.
It started at 210.
Oh, let's go back.
Yeah.
So we had it set up to 210.
Says wind direction
under true index.
Then we marked the velocity.
Then we twisted it a little bit.
So now, we've got
an index of south,
and we can read that our ground
speed will have fallen right
there under the little
grommet there to 129 knots,
and the wind correction angle
is going to be 4 degrees.
You can read that off of
this little scale here.
See, it says 5 and 10.
Anyway, so we do all of
that, which is very tedious.
It's based on a forecast,
again, of the winds aloft,
so it's never going
to be exactly right.
And we use it to fill out one
of these navigation log forms.
Once it's all
filled out, you can
see that it's a lot easier to
do if you just ask some computer
application to do it for you,
like SkyVector is free and will
do it for you, using
the forecast winds.
Then when you're flying
along, as I said,
you make corrections.
So here, for example,
unfortunately,
the one bad thing
about SkyVector,
I put in these user fixes,
a beam to Fitchburg Airport
and crossing the
Connecticut River,
I think, because I
thought those would
be easy to see from the air.
But unfortunately, there's no
way to name them in SkyVector.
So they just come
out as user fix.
But maybe you could write
that in with a pencil.
Anyway, so you can
see here, the wind
is forecast to be
from 272 at 15 knots.
You're going 140 knots
of true air speed.
Your track over the ground
is supposed to be 287 true,
minus 2 degrees wind
correction angle.
I just did this, actually,
for Sunday night, I think.
The true heading,
therefore, will be 285,
but then you'll have
to add 16 degrees
for the local variation.
So you'll end up with a
magnetic heading of 301.
So you steer that for a
while, see how it goes.
It's supposed to take you about
12 minutes from the time you
took off to the time
you reach that point.
And you write down
what actually happened.
And if you see the airport--
let's see, it's supposed
to be on our left.
If you see the
airport on your right,
you say, well, the wind's
not quite what I thought.
I'm going to steer
10 degrees right.
And then, that river
crossing, I guess,
isn't really ideal for
heading correction.
You probably want to find
some other landmarks as well.
All right.
Pilotage-- oh, question?
AUDIENCE: How far [INAUDIBLE]?
PHILIP GREENSPUN: They do.
Tina might know.
I think the winds aloft are
forecast either 24 or 30
hours in advance.
Yeah.
That's a good question.
We can look that
up for you later.
But yeah, so you can
predict, to some extent,
with prevailing winds.
Some of these applications
will work with averages
and so forth, if it's not there.
But yeah, within 24 hours,
you have a pretty good wind
forecast.
But again, with a
modern GPS system,
you can immediately see whether
you're going off course,
and the autopilot may
automatically make
the correction for you anyway.
So this is kind of a
historical lecture.
It's good to know.
What I would say is, well,
yeah, so what I would say
is, it's still worth doing, but
I would say generate the navlog
electronically.
It's not really worth doing
anymore, like the full pain.
The knowledge test does have
a built-in electronic E6B.
The tests are not
that demanding,
except that you will
need the plotter.
So they'll give you a supplement
with a bit of a chart,
and you need the
plotter to figure out
how far it is from place
to place on the real test.
That's if you want to get 100.
Yeah, you see the
summary of how it works.
It's a fun skill.
I will tell you, I
had two interactions
on basically the same day.
I met an alumna of this course
at the East Coast Aero Club,
and she was tearing
up a storm with an E6B
and filling out the
navlog, and doing all this.
I said, why are you doing that?
Every East Coast Aero Club
plane has a Garmin 430 in it.
Just punch in your
destination and you can go.
And if that doesn't work,
call up air traffic control
and tell them you're lost.
So she said, well, like every
flight with my instructor,
he fails everything.
He makes me go back and assume
that everything's broken
and do it all old
school and manually.
So she was doing this on every
cross-country flight that she
was doing, both dual and solo.
And I said, well, that's good.
I'm not sure how
much relationship
that has to safety because
the other interaction I had
that day was with a commercial
pilot, instrument rated, who
wanted to rent the Cirrus.
And I was the previous
user of the airplane.
So I said, how much
fuel do you want?
He said, I want it topped off.
I said, you're going
to fly for six hours?
Where you going?
He said, I'm going to Albany.
I said, well, it's an hour away.
What do you want six
hours of fuel for?
He said, the airport I'm going
to doesn't have any fuel.
I said, Albany, the
crosswind runway
there is longer than
Hanscom's main runway.
It's 7,500 feet.
They've got a beautiful FBO.
It's basically free.
What do you mean,
they have no fuel?
And he wanted to go
to this other airport.
It was on the east side of town.
It was actually farther
from his destination.
He was taking his
son to Rensselaer,
and the big airport's
actually closer.
And this was a 2,500-foot
airport with a note
in the chart supplement saying
to call a phone number before
you even try to go there, to
check out the local conditions.
It's unattended.
If you blow a tire,
there's no way
to get a mechanic out there
other than maybe driving
from Albany or Boston.
And it has a displaced
threshold too.
It's 2,500 feet, but because
of the trees on both ends,
you're not supposed to
land right on the numbers.
You actually land a few, like
500 feet or 400 feet down
the runway.
So I said, the Cirrus
takes about 2,100 feet
to land over a 50-foot obstacle.
So you're budgeting
to use more than 60%
of the runway, which the
airline minimum is, you
have to plan to land in 60%.
That way if you are
a little bit sloppy,
you don't go off the end of
the runway and hit something.
So I said, why would you
give yourself, with your son,
less safety margin than
a two-pilot airline crew?
And so he said,
well, I don't want
to deal with an FBO, which
was really weird to me.
So basically, there's no point
to that story other than--
no, there is a
point to that story.
There is no point to that story.
Safety is not about doing
everything really tedious.
It's more about having
reasonable judgment and asking,
why am I better than a
two-pilot airline crew?
So yeah, she was smart.
She's an engineer
so of course, it
doesn't overtax her to
do this kind of stuff,
but let's not really confuse
it with adding safety, which
is more about having the
judgment to know when to take
a co-pilot or when to
make your life easier
by going to an airport
with a really long runway.
All right.
Let's talk about ADFs.
This was very exciting in 1952.
Have a look there.
That was a Lear.
Some of you have probably
heard of Lear Jet.
So the founder of
Lear Jet was also
the inventor of the first
practical car radios.
So all the money that
was made on car radios
was eventually turned
into an aviation company,
and before the Lear Jet,
there were these avionics
that made it super
easy to figure out
where the station was.
I think at the very first,
the pilot would tune,
or the navigator more
likely would twist this dial
and hear when this tone
reached some kind of maximum.
Then there was the
automatic direction finder,
which would just point the
needle in that direction
of the station.
See here, it's just pointing.
Yeah, here's something.
This is from the
pilots handbook,
I think, on how to use an NDB.
But you can see that
with a heavy wind,
you don't end up really tracking
exactly towards the station.
All right.
So relative bearing is how
far to your left or your right
the station is.
And then you can get
the magnetic bearing
if you add your own
heading in there.
So this is not rocket science.
If you're going south, and
the station is 90 degrees
to your left, then the magnetic
bearing to the station is going
to be, I guess, well, I guess
the bearing to the station
would be 090, in that case.
All right.
This was an exciting thing
where you could actually
turn the card on your ADF.
So if you were heading
northwest of a heading of 330,
you would twist that
and then you just,
without having to
think, you can see
that you have to fly
roughly with no wind.
You would fly 210 to
get to the station.
I guess some planes that
operate in Europe a lot,
they were requiring
this to later.
Planes that just have a
lot of stuff on the panel
still may have this,
but in general, they're
hard to find now.
VORs are still around.
They have 360 radials that
the radio receiver can just
identify.
So the receiver can just say,
I know that I am exactly south
or I know that I'm exactly east
or I know that I'm exactly 060
direction from this station.
So you'll be able to
know where you are,
and if you can tune
in two different ones,
and you've got your
handy pencil out,
and your chart, in the aircraft,
you can draw intersecting lines
and figure out where
you are on the chart.
So again, in the
moving map GPS days,
this is not as exciting
a skill as it once was.
I think there are
a few questions
about the symbols on the chart
for different kinds of VORs.
So one thing is distance
measuring equipment,
whereby sending out a pulse
and having the station send
that back to the aircraft,
it's possible by measuring
the transit time to actually get
your distance in nautical miles
read out to you in the cockpit.
Be advised that's the actual
distance through the air,
so it's not the
horizontal distance
projected over the ground.
But if you're up a few
miles, it might be,
and if you're close to the VOR,
it might be slightly different.
Service volumes-- there
are these terminal VORs.
I think a lot of them
may be decommissioned
or being decommissioned now.
But the FAA has made
various kinds of VORs.
These high altitude
ones will probably
be the last to go because
actually, with airliners,
the certification costs of
new avionics are so high
that the last aircraft
flying without a GPS
will be some huge Boeing.
It won't be a Piper or
a Steerman or something.
OK.
The parts of the VOR--
so you have this thing called
the Omni Bearing Selector which
you can tune here, and on the
canonical instrument here,
all it does is rotate
this card around the top.
So that is to pick out the
radial that you want, and then
you get the To/From flag.
So you can see here,
this is showing you
that the 360 radial
is off to your left.
And if we were to fly--
we don't have to.
This is not related
to the actual heading
of the aircraft-- but if we
were to fly basically north,
we'd be going away from the VOR.
OK.
We're going to get
into this more.
The HSI down there offers
you the same information,
but superimposed on the
aircraft's actual heading,
which makes life a lot easier.
OK.
How do you test your VOR
and know that it's actually
going to work?
There are these
VOR test stations,
or VOTs, test facilities.
If you can remember
Cessna 182, every VOT
puts out the same signal,
and what you should see
is an indication of
2 when you dial up,
and it should be centered
on the 180 radial.
So that's how you know
if your VOR is working.
If you're going to use
it for instrument flight,
you have to test
them every 30 days.
All right.
Let's have a look.
You're going to probably
have to study and think
about this a little
bit more at home.
But one easy way
to think about this
is to build yourself
a virtual HSI.
So if you see a test question,
and it shows the indicator set
up to tune to like
the 030 radial,
just draw a little airplane or
imagine an airplane actually
heading northeast
on a 030 heading.
So you can see this
airplane at left, this one,
it's showing that the 030 radial
is to the right of the wing,
assuming we were
actually heading 030,
and that we're going vaguely
towards the VOR because the To
flag is set up.
Over here, it's the same,
but it's the From flag.
Over here on the right, we've
got the radial off to our left,
and we're going From
the VOR over here.
Again, the radial's to our
left and we're going To.
So just let that
sink in a little bit.
I think I'm going to show you
an FAA written test question,
so you just know.
It says, the VOR's turned
to the Elizabeth City VOR.
That, I believe, is right over--
if you want to know the
value of a marketing degree,
this Elizabeth City is
right next to a big place
called the Dismal Swamp,
the Dismal Swamp Park.
Anyway, so if you're anywhere
near the Dismal Swamp,
and you want to go visit,
and you're at Elizabeth City,
tune to the VOR.
It says the aircraft is
positioned over Shawboro.
One of the hardest
things about this
is finding Shawboro on the map.
But I've drawn it there for you.
So we're northeast
of the VOR, and it
says, which VOR indication is
correct, 2 which is at the top
there, 8 or 9 on the bottom?
What do you guys think?
So we're northeast of Shawboro.
Who wants to vote for 2?
210 from.
Nobody?
Who wants to vote for 8?
That's 0302.
Who wants to vote for 9?
A few hands?
Yay.
OK.
So basically, we're
right on the radial.
So Shawboro, you can
see here at the end
of the arrow, it is, I think,
that actually might say--
I don't know what
that says, actually.
I have no idea.
10, 20, 30, yeah, it's
right there at the 30.
OK.
So it's definitely
on the 030 radial,
which is also the 210
radial, the reciprocal.
I mean, this is not a
totally trivial question.
But if we were to fly
210, we would be going To.
The flag should be To.
If we were actually
flying southwest,
we'd be heading towards the
VOR, so it should be a To flag.
If we're flying away from
the VOR, further out on 030,
and it should be a From
flag which is not an 8,
and this one is the only one
that's consistent because if we
actually were to fly 030, we'd
be going away from the VOR.
Don't sweat it if
you haven't got it.
There is actually
a cool simulator
in Adobe Flash which
was actually cool
when you guys were born.
And AOPA, also, I have linked
here to the Airplane Owners
and Pilots Association,
the big lobbying
group for private aviation.
They have a list of--
I don't think they're
free, unfortunately.
That web simulator is free.
But there's little
simulators you
can get on your phone for VORs.
That used to be
really important.
I mean, GPS is now more
important, basically.
It was a 1973 US military idea.
If you just broadcast
the time and the position
of a bunch of satellites
from the satellites,
then the receiver
can see how long
did it take to get
from the satellite
to where the receiver is.
So if you think about it, let's
say one of the transmitters
is by that exit sign.
So if I know my distance
from the exit sign,
that puts me on a sphere
of uncertainty, right?
I could be up in the ceiling.
I could be down on
the first floor.
I could be in a lot
of different places,
as long as I know that I'm--
let's call it 30 feet
from the exit sign.
OK.
Well, that's not great
because I'm still pretty
uncertain about where I am.
But how about if there's
another transmitter
in that corner of the room,
that gives me a second sphere.
Two spheres will intersect
in a circle, I believe.
So now we have a
circle of uncertainty.
And we pick up another
transmitter maybe somewhere
over there.
So the more
satellites we can see,
the more intersecting
spheres we have,
and eventually, we'll get down
to a very small little area
of uncertainty, indeed.
So that's how GPS works.
You just rely on the fact that
the speed of light is constant.
If you know the distance to
each of a bunch of satellites,
and you know where they
are, then at that point,
you know where you are.
The 32 satellites,
as of 2016, were up.
31 were in use.
You can always see five.
For IFR, the idea is to
try to get some redundancy.
There are some tweaks
to that system.
I think what I just
described would work really
well in outer space where
there's no atmosphere
to bend or distort any
of the radio signals.
But there is a certain amount
of distortion that happens,
and there are these
ground-based reference stations.
So you know exactly
where they are.
They don't move.
And they listen to the signals.
And they try to figure
out how much error there
is as a result of
the signals traveling
through the atmosphere
at that location.
Those corrections are then
pushed back up into space
and sent back down
from the satellites
to ordinary receivers.
And with those corrections,
you can become really accurate.
You can get accurate
enough to actually fly
down right towards the runway.
So the GPS system which launched
in the mid-'90s, that enabled
the moving map, and you
never were lost again.
You always knew where you were.
But the WAAS system
is what enables
these GPS approaches where
you navigate in 3D to within--
I don't know-- 10 feet or
something of precision,
right down to the runway.
All right.
What does it look
like in practice?
This is the pilot's view.
This is a modern Garmin 750.
It's a single box that
actually has three sub boxes,
and the sub boxes are
the GPS, a nav radio,
which lets you tune up VORs
and instrument landing system
for approaching a runway.
Tina may talk about that
a little bit tomorrow
in a little IFR intro,
and also a com radio,
And they actually, I
think they actually
have three separate
power supplies.
So there's a
connection to the box,
maybe for power,
but after that you
can have tremendous amount
of failure inside the box
and still have a subset
of the functions working.
I guess if the
screen fails, you're
out of luck, which is why every
IFR certified airplane that I
know of that's newish has a
second one of these, usually
smaller, a Garmin 650,
which is physically smaller.
The Garmin G1000,
it's even bigger.
It's on this huge
multifunction display.
If that fails, you can
swap all the information
over to the primary flight
display or vice versa.
So that just gives you
a little view to it.
Here's your com
radio on the G1000,
and here's your nav radio,
and see, it's even identified.
The VORs put out a
Morse code signal,
and the Garmin
has listened to it
and identified it as the
PPG VOR, the FJR VOR.
All right.
The G1000, actually, this is
one of the worst human factors
design I think I've ever seen.
Wonder who else
can identify this.
Like what is truly
terrible about this design?
I'll give you a hint.
Well, there's the all the
engine instruments on the left
there too.
So what kind of pretty common
failure, accident causing
failure, does this really
not help you prevent?
Electrical-- that's
not very common.
And I'll tell you that most
airplanes that have an accident
are in perfect mechanical,
electrical, and sheet metal
condition.
AUDIENCE: Fuel starvation?
PHILIP GREENSPUN:
Fuel starvation.
Yeah, like your
battery, your amps.
I mean, basically, fuel
is given the same status
as all of this stuff.
Fuel is almost always relevant.
And this other stuff is
almost never relevant.
And here it is.
It's small.
As you run out of
fuel, as you get really
down into the red zone,
does this thing grow?
You think it would grow to
consume half of the display.
But It doesn't do
anything like that.
So I think it's a
terrible, terrible design,
and aviation really
needs some help.
Avidyne is a little better, I
think, on the user interface.
This is kind of a legacy
system from the Cirrus.
This is NEXRAD
data link weather.
We're going to talk about
that in a little bit.
Here is just a little
thing about navigation.
If you're going anywhere
near the DC area,
either get your instrument
rating and file IFR,
and then it becomes
like everywhere else,
or you have to take this
online course at some point
and learn about the special
rules in the DC area.
They're not that hard to
go down to Gaithersburg.
You have to VFR.
You have to go in
from certain gates.
You have to file a
flight plan in advance,
and you have to keep a unique
transponder code so that air
traffic control can track you.
So if you have any brilliant
ideas for how folks in DC
could do things
better, you can just
get in a little Piper
or Cessna or Cirrus
at Hanscom, zip down
to Gaithersburg,
and there you are.
All right.
After the navigation
mistakes, so
let's say you bust into
class Bravo airspace
without a clearance, or
do something else that you
shouldn't have done.
The FAA and NASA are really
not there to bust you.
There's this special
form you can fill out
where you if you
write down what you
did, why you did it,
how you think things
could be improved--
maybe it was a user
interface issue.
Maybe somebody else was
using the airplane before you
and turned off all
the airspace alerts.
You just fill out this
form and mail it in,
and that limits the
amount of discipline
that they can subject you to.
I mean it doesn't protect you
from intentional violations.
All right.
Here's a summary.
Pilotage, NDBs, VOR, and GPS.
That was the progression.
You've seen, now, 100 years
of aviation navigation.
Actually, one thing
that I hope this does
is give you a new
appreciation for some
of the achievements of people
who flew around the world
in the '60s or the '50s.
There's a woman, Jerrie
Mock, I think, is her name.
A great book.
She flew a Cessna tail dragger
around the world in the 1960s.
And she was often lost.
She'd be over the ocean
with icing on her wings.
She would be having to track
NDBs in Egypt or whatever.
So all of that stuff has
gotten so much easier,
it's almost not fair.
And you've got these data links.
So we can't compare
our achievements
to the achievements
of pilots or the risks
that we're taking to
the risks that folks
were taking in the old days.
They didn't have EPIRBs
if they went in the water.
They didn't have moving maps.
So they just didn't know where
they were most of the time.
They had a vague idea.
All right.
So this is for Francis.
This is a quote from Captain
Sully's book, the single pilot
Airbus hero, according
to most of you.
So he's got a failed GPS and
a failed compass, Francis.
He says he could just keep
Venus in the left front
corner of the windshield, and
we would reach California.
What else could
Captain Sully have
done as an alternative
to using Venus?
AUDIENCE: The sun?
PHILIP GREENSPUN: The sun?
Well, it's nighttime.
What?
AUDIENCE: Polaris?
PHILIP GREENSPUN: Polaris.
AUDIENCE: Follow Route 90?
PHILIP GREENSPUN: Yes,
actually, the helicopter
follow an interstate highway.
That's a common
helicopter technique,
probably because the
interstates always
go through the lowest points.
How about this one?
Request vectors SFO.
You could probably climb
right out of Hanscom
and call it Boston
approach, and they would
be happy to help at any time.
Actually, that is
a good question.
That's actually a good point
into crew resource management.
Don't try to be a
single pilot hero.
Ideally, if it's a challenging
flight, you've got a co-pilot,
and even if you don't
have a co-pilot,
you always have air traffic
control as another crew member.
All right.
Let's take a few questions.
Who's got questions
about navigation?
AUDIENCE: In your
[INAUDIBLE] use for GPS
signal at certain altitude?
PHILIP GREENSPUN: Ah.
So the question is,
can the airplane
show you your true altitude
based on the GPS signal?
And it's buried in there.
It can't be shown
on your altimeter
in your primary flight display.
But you can dig it out
of either a separated
GPS like the Garmin 750 or
430, or the integrated glass
panels like the G1000.
AUDIENCE: Still the [INAUDIBLE]?
PHILIP GREENSPUN: Yes.
What you're navigating
from, how you're
being separated
from other aircraft,
that's all based on
the static information.
But if you just want to
see, I know that mountain's
8,000 feet high, I want to
make sure it says at least 8001
for the actual altitude,
you can dig that out.
And I think the terrain
warning system will use that.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
an older aircraft,
does it have the
GPS or [INAUDIBLE]??
What are the rules
and regulations
about using GPS [INAUDIBLE]?
PHILIP GREENSPUN: Yes.
I'll repeat the question
back for the tape and anybody
who didn't hear.
So this phone has more computing
power and better design
than everything inside a
Boeing 747 or an Airbus A380.
In fact, I talked to
some Airbus A320 captains
and they said they wanted
to get rid of everything
in the airplane except
the altitude indicator,
and they just wanted
to navigate off
of an iPad running
a European app
called Sky Demon, which is kind
of like the American forefather
of Garmin pilot.
They said, that would
be just way better,
to just use the
iPad for everything.
So as a practical matter,
in your ancient airplane
that might not even have
an electrical system, yes,
of course, you can
navigate quite effectively
with some battery-powered
electronics
or portable electronics that
you stick around the aircraft.
And the interface
can be very good,
and they have comprehensive
databases of everything
you'd want to know.
For legal purposes,
and for practical ones,
for instrument flying,
you have to have
FAA certified stuff that's
hardwired to the aircraft
and it's in the panel.
And that makes sense
because, think about it,
your phone may die.
The battery may die.
So it's nice to have.
If you want to do an
instrument approach,
for example, you're
going to need
to have something like-- even an
experimental airplane-- you've
got to have one of those
certified, like a Garmin
750 in there.